RAG from scratch project:

I’m planning to build a RAG pipeline from scratch without using amazon bedrock or auto services.
My current project planned are:
1. docs (I will take some text already in document under .txt format or something, no need to preprocessing) → chunking → embedding --> store in vector database. Then we build the HNSW indexes from the vector database 
2. When user enter query → query gets embedded → search the vector database using the HNSW index we pre built (fast) —> then return the relevant chunks → we then rerank them using a reranker model → then pass to the LLM with the prompt = user query + relevant chunks → output the answer.

How do you note of this project? Is the pipeline looking good?

—————
I’m having some technical question regarding the model selection in the pipeline:
- should I use langchain or I should do it from scratch without any framework?
- what would the be a suitable chunking strategy?
- what embedding model should I choose? Should I choose from openai or opensource?
- what would be the choice of vector database?
- how would we build the HNSW index? saying we cannt run locally because we dont have compute power, do we need ec2 or what other good aws services like ECS or lambda?
- what should be the reranker model?

If we use cloud compute power from AWS,  we dont need to use openai api for the ease of simplicity, we can use open source model if the set up of the compute resources is simple forward. 

——————
choice of embedding model: BAAI / bge-large-en-v1.5 or qwen-embedding-8B

choice of reranker model: bge-reranker-large or ZeroEntropy zerank-1

vector database is FAISS + HNSW? I thought FAISS is a library. How it can be a vector database?

llm: Llama 3.1 8B
——————
for vector database I would want to use a vector database product but which one is the best in our case and free: pinecone, milvus, weaviate? and we also build hnsw as search index
—————
if i use pinecone, for embedding, search indexing, reranking, can my computer run locally? my computer is macbook air m1 8gb ram
—————
say we choose openai because our macbook air isnt sufficent, what would be the open ai model choice for embedding, reranker, llm

so if we search for vectors, does pinecone use hybrid search with bm25?

so if I perform the faiss hnsw manually, how we would do that? walk through easy step by step. 

———
To answer your questions for refinement:
- I thought you cannot really configure specific hnsw index parameters on pinecone? Is that true or you can configure it
- Let’s do sentence split for chunking strategy 
- I don’t have a specific retry strategies or rate limiting patterns you want documented for the OpenAI/Pinecone API calls. Recommend me the implementation
- Yes, guidance would be good on testing strategies (unit tests for chunking, integration tests for the pipeline)
- I want to change top-k = 15 to 10 
——————————
explain those library below: 
- tenacity library for exponential backoff with jitter
- ltk.sent_tokenize() or spacy for sentence splitting
- Use tiktoken (encoding: cl100k_base) 

ltk.sent_tokenize() or spacy
———————
fix: adjust the architecture and frameworks planning
- Specified nltk.sent_tokenize() - Removed spacy reference for clarity
- Added detailed chunking workflow - 6-step process from reading document.txt through storing in Pinecone
- Updated file architecture - Added docs/ folder for documentation markdown files
——————

============
I have some notes on the call_openai method that:
- GPT-5 does not support the temperature parameter in its API; it's locked to a default of 1.0
- For GPT-5 models, the older max_tokens parameter is often unsupported, causing errors; you should use max_completion_tokens

